Let’s start discussing Access Control Lists
For simplicity, let’s assume each user is
associated with one domain and that all processes
ran by the user belong to such domain.
In the example, we have a user A and his/her
processes also belong to domain A.
We define one access control list per file.
As the name suggests, it is a list, and it
is scanned in order, stopping at the first
entry that matches.
If no rights are found for a given domain,
then we assume such a domain as no rights
associated with it.
The entry can contain the usual permissions
for reading (R) writing (W) and executing
(X) but nothing prevents a system from defining
more rights.
An important aspect here is how we implement
such a system. More concretely, what are the
specific elements we store in each entry?
First, we can distinguish rights for individuals
and for groups (the latter are useful when
we want to apply the same rights to a set
of individuals that share some features, e.g.,
students).
Then, we can store rights as pairs .
In this case, we refer to them as ROLES, since
each set of rights is associated not only
to a user but also to the group such user
is representing (and one user could in principle
be associated with multiple groups).
In such a case, we could also use wildcards,
to define rights that apply to a user independently
of each group ().
An alternative implementation is to store
rights on a per-user / per-group basis.
Revoking or granting permissions is simple
using access control lists.
Let’s say we want to change the rights associated
with user A so that user A can no longer do
anything with file F1.
If we append to the ACL of F1 the pair =(none)
then this will be always the first entry matched
for user A, and user A will thus have no rights
for file F1.
Notice though we might want to clean and keep
our access control list in order, to prevent
it from ever-growing.